Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights 1984-2003 GLBTQ.2012.07
Elihu Burritt Library, GLBTQ Archives
Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights, 1984-2003
GLBTQ.2012.07
GLBTQ Archives
2.5 Linear feet
The Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights (CCLGCR) was an organization prominent during the 1980’s and 1990’s for standing up for GLBTQ civil rights. They avidly fundraised, made a presence in political discussions and rallies, and created a safe zone for homosexuals in the state. This collection includes the group’s organizational documents, fundraising efforts, and newspaper articles, along with other related items.
Biographical/Historical note
Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights (CCLGCR) was formed during the summer of 1983 by a group of gay men and women discouraged by the continued defeat of the Gay Civil Rights Bill. They decided to form a statewide organization dedicated to the passage of civil rights legislation regarding discrimination based on sexual orientation. The coalition worked with progressive political organizations, other minority groups, religious affiliates, educators, and legal, social, and healthcare professionals to develop a lesbian and gay community. In 1985, the group established four regions throughout the state. In 1986, the group added “Connecticut” to the beginning of their name, becoming the CT CLGCR, in order to be able to back political candidates according to state law. The Political Action Committee was thus formed in 1988. The PAC interviewed candidates and reported the information back to the coalition, focusing mainly on areas of importance for homosexuals. The establishment of the PAC also led to inclusion in the statewide Legislative Electoral Action Program (LEAP), strengthening the CT CLGCR’s voice in the state government. Other projects initiated by CCLGCR were Stop the Hate and Love Makes a Family. In 1989, the group organized the HIV Task Force which was created to deal with legislative issues involving HIV and AIDS by writing position papers and making suggestions to the rest of the coalition. Another project was called The Anti-Violence Project, following the murder of a Connecticut gay man in 1988. Immediately following this incident, the AVP was created to monitor the murder case but also created Speak Out! in 1989. This program supplied organizations, school, and other interested parties with a participating speaker on homosexual issues. They also focused on the Hate Crimes Bill in 1990 pushing for its passage in conjunction with several other groups. The Religious Task Force was created in 1991 to organize the state’s religious community in support of the Gay Rights Bill. Later, the group changed its name to include transgender individuals, becoming CCLGBTCR. By 1999, the group was organized in six congressional districts and supported issues in the legislature such as anti-discrimination laws for students K-12, private right of action, health issues support such as HIV/AIDS and breast cancer, domestic partner benefits for state employees, and opposition to any state law prohibiting same gender marriage. In 2000, CCLGBTCR embarked on the Diversity Project to expand the membership base by meeting with diverse communities in the state, raise the level of awareness for the coalition, and assist communities in overcoming barriers that hinder their participation in the work of the coalition.
Scope and Contents note
This collection includes documents relating directly to the Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights in addition to articles, advertisements, and correspondence during the time period of 1984-2003.
Related Archival Materials note
An oral history interview of Carolyn Gabel-Brett is available within the Digital Collections of the GLTBQ Archives on the website of the Elihu Burritt Library.
Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights.; Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights; Gay liberation movement -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Hate crimes -- Connecticut -- Legislative history; Homosexuality -- Connecticut -- Hartford -- Periodicals; Homosexuality -- Connecticut -- Periodicals; Homosexuality -- Families; Homosexuality -- Law and legislation -- United States -- Periodicals; Same-sex marriage -- Connecticut
- CCLGCR- Letterhead (Box 1, Folder 1)
- CCLGCR- History (Box 1, Folder 2)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes/agendas, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- CCLGCR- Membership Survey, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- CCLGCR- Membership Lists/ labels (Box 1, Folder 13)
- CCLGCR- Middlesex Chapter- Meeting minutes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- CCLGCR- Legislative initiative- Bulletins, legislation, articles, announcements (Missing 4 items), 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Gabel, Carolyn- Legislative update, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 15 Workshop programs for dealing with different situations, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- CCLGCR - Steering Committee meetings - minutes, agendas, flyers, events., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- CCLGCR - Steering Committee meetings - minutes, agendas, flyers, events., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- CCLGCR - Steering Committee meetings - minutes, agendas, flyers, events., 1990
- CCLGCR- Steering Committee minutes, letters to legislators, legislative information, newspaper articles, Committee Bill 7584, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- CCLGCR- Press releases, event flyers, Steering Committee minutes, testimonies, legislative information, newspaper articles, Committee Bill 7584, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- CCLGCR- Press releases, event flyers, testimonies, legislative information, newspaper articles, Committee Bill 7584, lobbying plans, AIDS brochures, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- CCLGCR- Press releases, event flyers, testimonies, legislative information, newspaper articles, Committee Bill 7584, lobbying plans, AIDS brochures, Part 2., 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- CCLGCR- Press releases, event flyers, testimonies, legislative information, newspaper articles, Committee Bill 7584, lobbying plans, AIDS brochures, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- CCLGCR- Meeting minutes, legislative issues/questionnaires, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Imperial Court of Connecticut- Brochures,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Imperial Court of Connecticut- Applications, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Imperial Court of Connecticut-Certificate of Title for members (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Imperial Court of Connecticut- 50’s and 60’s Benefit Dance flyers, fundraiser forms, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Imperial Court of Connecticut- The Nutmeg Empire, New London County Barony- Fundraiser financial statements, newspaper articles, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Imperial Court of Connecticut- Adornment of New Haven County, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Imperial Court of Connecticut- Adornment of New London County, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Imperial Court of Connecticut- The Investiture: The Naming of the Second Royal Dynasty of the Imperial Court of Connecticut- Flyers, ticket information, guest list, Hartford, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Imperial Court of Rhode Island- Coronation III “A Night in Camelot,”, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- “Imperial: The Imperial Court System Marks 30 Years By Celebrating the Many Faces of Drag” San Francisco Frontiers(Richard Stillson quoted) 2 Copies, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Imperial Jewels v. 1 no. 1, Spring, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Official International Imperial Court Calendar. (Explanation of system)., 1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Boyden, Rebecca, “The House of Pleasure: A Social Organization in Hartford’s Gay Community”; Articles about other Houses., 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- House of Pleasure- “Murder is a Drag” show program and advertisements, meeting agendas, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- House of Pleasures - Snowball 3, 1995 & Snowball, 4 1996- Programs (Box 3, Folder 15)
- House of Pleasures- Snowball 5- Program and newspaper article, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- House of Pleasures Poster- “Night Train” Ball benefit, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- “Mother Love Rick ‘Mucha Mucha’ Stillson Proves Why Queens Rule” by William J. Mann, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- House of Everlasting Empire- 1st Annual Ball Awards program, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Hartford Pride PAC- Statement of receipts and expenditures, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- McNaught, Brian- “What is Gay Pride?” (Box 3, Folder 21)
- OUT! Awards- Planning notes, winners, menu, advertising, press releases, program, brochures from sponsors, nominations (Box 3, Folder 22)
- OUT! Awards- Program, photos, advertising, article, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- OUT! Awards- Program, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Hartford Rainbow Flag Raising Ceremony- Speech, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Rick Stillson- Biographical information, 1999; 2003 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Dragona- 2 hand drawn sketches (plans for a float?) (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Imperial Court and Houses Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Trip to Toronto fundraiser, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Miscellaneous organizational documents, news articles (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Domestic Partnership Ordinance- Articles, legislation, Hartford, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Domestic Partnership Benefits- Notes from meetings, articles, testimonies, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Defense Of Marriage Act and domestic partner benefits information- Report on costs and benefits, articles, meeting notes, fact sheets, Hawaii and Massachusetts same-sex marriage information, 1997-2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Domestic Partnership Commission, Hartford- Correspondence, meeting notes, lobby plans, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Domestic Partnership Arbitration Hearing, 2000 & related articles, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- “Collective Bargaining Agreement Between The University of Connecticut Board of Trustees and UCONN Professional Employees Association, 1994-1997” (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Love Makes A Family- Meeting agendas, organizational papers, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund, Inc.- Memorandum regarding the marriage resolution and new language used in the statement, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- National Gay and Lesbian Task Force- “To Have and to Hold: Organizing for our Right to Marry,”, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Southern Poverty Law Center (SPLC)-“Ten Ways to Fight Hate”, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- National Association of Black and White Men Together (NABWMT)- “Manual for Discrimination Response Systems”, 1988? (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Connecticut Anti-Violence Project- Event announcements, newspaper articles, discrimination legislation, meeting minutes regarding project, letters of support for anti-violence legislation, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Homophobia training- Documents regarding prevention of homophobia, notes, events, MacDonald Jr., A.P. “Homophobia: Its Roots and Meanings,”, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- “Striking Back at Bigotry”- A compilation of Connecticut laws, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- “A collection of letters, statements, and listings which documents the broad based support within Connecticut’s religious community for legislation prohibiting discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation.” (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Stop the Hate Project- Meeting minutes, promotions, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Discrimination in schools- Newspaper articles, other resources, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Sex Education in Schools- Articles (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Central Connecticut State University mailing- Event, “15 years of LGBTQ History in Connecticut”, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Carrera, Reverend Gabriel- “Hispanics for Christian Family Values,” Press release, newspaper articles, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Metropolitan Community Church, Hartford- Brief history, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Capital Region Conference of Churches- The Committee on Sexual Minorities- Brief history, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Greater Hartford HIV Action Initiative- Priorities and goals, 1993-1994; 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- AIDS events and newspaper articles related to Connecticut, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Metroline Editorial Board- Meeting notes, list of board members, correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Stonewall Reenactment Skit, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Amnesty International- “Gay Rights”, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Political Research Associates- “Ground Rules and Tips for Challenging the Right”, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Politics- Legislation unrelated to GLBTQ issues, list of politicians, advertising, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- CCLGCR - Lobbying efforts for gaining support for gay and lesbian civil rights, related documents., 1987-1989; Materials in container 6 was forwarded to the Burritt Librar by Carolyn Gable Brett in August 2015. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- CCLGCR - Lobbying efforts for gaining support for gay and lesbian civil rights, press clippings, flyers., 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- CCLGCR - Lobbying efforts for gaining support for gay and lesbian civil rights, press., 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- CCLGCR - Political Action Committee, by laws, minutes., 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- CCLGCR - Religious Task Force, reports, memos, clippings., 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- CCLGCR - Collection of letters, statements, and listings which documents support in CT religious community prohibiting discrimination based on sexual orientation., 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- CCLGCR - Lobbying efforts for gaining support for gay and lesbian civil rights, Bill #7133., 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Strategiesthat passed the gay, lesbian and heterosexual rights Bill#7133, written by Paul Wensley., April 29, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- CCLGCR - Civil Rights Bill #7133, letters, testimonials of Victor D'LLugin, Daniel Livingston, Janice Warren, Brigitte Albert., 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- CCLGCR - Civil Rights Bill #7133, clippings., April 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Connecticut religious communities supports civil rights for gay and lesbian in CT., 1991 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- CCLGCR - report on supporting organizations., 1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- CCLGCR - Tolland/Windham Chapter,membership, correspondence, newsletters., 1988-1991 (Box 6, Folder 13)